<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Character of an Irish-man, or, A dear-joy painted to the life</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31730</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2012</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9048</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13274795</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13274795</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98710</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31730)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98710)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 450:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Character of an Irish-man, or, A dear-joy painted to the life</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.]</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1688-1689 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98710:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98710:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->
            <head>THE CHARACTER OF AN Irish-Man: OR, A DEAR-JOY <hi>Painted to the Life.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SINCE the Arrival of the <hi>Teague-Land</hi> Troops, in this <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Kingdom, who can admire at the ſurprize and conſternation of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, when they look upon it to be as bad as a New Maſſacre, and much more Formidable than a <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TCH</hi>-Invaſion?
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98710:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->But, if this be the Effect of our Fears, Where's our Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude? Where's our True <hi>Engliſh</hi> Courage? Where's our Ancient Grandeur? Can it be conſiſtent with the Temper of a true <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Man, whoſe Name has been a Terror to all Nations, to fear a Neighbouring Subject? Is it not a Diminution of that Ancient Glory that once kept all the Univerſe in awe? <hi>England</hi> fear'd no Incurſions then, but made them. Our War-like Kings, like <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> came and ſaw, and whereſo-e're they came did Overcome: And ſhall we ſtand in dread of ſuch a Morſel, as would hardly ſerve the <hi>Bull-and-Mouth</hi> for a Break-faſt, before a long-winded Meeting? If they be Strangers, we ought to treat them with Civility: If they be Fellow-Subjects, we ought to Embrace them: If they come to our Aſſiſtance, we ought to Encourage them.</p>
            <p>But you'll Reply, They are a pack of <hi>Iriſh-Wolves, Tories, Cut-Throats, Papiſts,</hi> what not, come over to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour us.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, If they be <hi>Wolves,</hi> you have <hi>Doggs</hi> enough to Worry them, at a cheaper Rate than <hi>Cromwel</hi> did thoſe in <hi>Ireland.</hi> If they be <hi>Tories,</hi> we have yet <hi>Whiggs</hi> enough remaining of the old Stamp to match their Cocks. For <hi>Cut-Throats,</hi> (thank the Fates) ſome can Sleep quietly all Night, and when they Wake, find their <hi>Throats</hi> Cut in the Morning, without the help of an <hi>Iriſh-Skein.</hi> And for <hi>Papiſts,</hi> you have a Thouſand to One.</p>
            <p>Where then is the cauſe of our Fears and Jealouſies? It is a groundleſs Suſpition; and I will undertake to prove, by Invincible Arguments, that an <hi>Iriſh-Man,</hi> and Subject of the King of <hi>England,</hi> is no ſuch Monſter as you would render Him.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98710:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> They are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> as well as We, the ſame Hopes, the ſame Fears, and ſame Apprehenſions of a Future Being. If we differ in Principles, they have yet as much Honor and Honeſty, Allegiance and Loyalty, Religion and Conſcience, perhaps more than thoſe that ſuſpect their Fidelity.</p>
            <p>They are Subjects of the ſame Prince; ſubject to the ſame Laws and Puniſhments; Ought we not then to Love our Fellow-Subjects? What tho' we Arrogate to our ſelves the upper-hand in Fellowſhip? Muſt we therefore utterly deſpiſe theſe Gentlemen? 'Tis unnatural to take the Sword in the Right Hand to cut off the Left: We are all Members of the ſame Head.</p>
            <p>They are Civiliz'd as much as We; a Nation of as much Humanity, Temperance, and Sobriety: But you will ſay, They want Senſe, They want Courage; It is a Mercy, if they want them not more themſelves, who tax Them with the want of Either: For their Courage, ſhew me a Hector of <hi>Holbourn,</hi> that can Bully them; and for their want of Wit, (for all your <hi>Bog-Witticiſms,</hi> wherewith you upbraid them) produce the Sharper that can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ite them. If Diamond only can cut Diamond, 'tis odds but the <hi>Iriſh-Man</hi> has the better of the Lay: And for their Behaviour, inſtance ſo many? Men of any Nation, under the ſame Circumſtance, that e're carry'd themſelves with more <hi>Decorum,</hi> Obligingneſs, and Reſpect than they have done, in their Quarters or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, ſince their Arrival: Their Officers being generally. Gentlemen of Education, Conduct, and Experience.</p>
            <p>I will not deny, but amongſt ſo many Thouſands, there may be ſome Extravagancies committed; but ſhall we lay it as a Crime to a whole Nation? It is a ſmall Corporation, that has neither Rogue nor Thief within it; and that <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> has both, you need go no further than the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98710:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->to be convinc'd: It is uncharitable to condemn a whole Nation, for the particular Offences of a few.</p>
            <p>Nor will you find the leaſt cauſe of any ſuch danger from the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> there being amongſt them ſeveral <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Officers, which are <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> yet live amicably with their Superior Commanders, and the Soldiers quietly under them: Beſides, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> which are this day in <hi>Ireland,</hi> (where the Natives are more numerous) enjoy their Eſtates and Poſſeſſions, without the leaſt diſturbance or moleſtation.</p>
            <p>How unreaſonable is it then, to ſuſpect an <hi>Iriſh-Invaſion</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> by a few Regiments, when our vaſt Armies in <hi>Ireland</hi> cou'd hardly reduce them in ſo many Centuries?</p>
            <p>Let us then no more fear them as Enemies, but embrace them as Friends; and ſince they are only come over for the Defence of the King and Country, upbraid them no more with the Opprobrious Titles of <hi>Rogues, Tories,</hi> and <hi>Rebels;</hi> but call them (what they more properly deſerve) <hi>The Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Angels of the Court, The Life-Guard of the City, The Safe-guard of the Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed in the Year 1689.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98710:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
